<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>BPI</title>
		<description>bpi.cam.ac.uk</description>
		<link></link>
		<atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>2021 REF results published</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The results of the REF2021 assessment have been published, with the University of Cambridge and the BPI’s parent departments once again being ranked among the best in the country. Our Earth Sciences department ranked highest overall in their field, producing work that is “world-leading in terms of originality, significance and rigour”, and our Chemistry, Engineering and Mathematical Sciences departments were similarly acclaimed, coming second nationally in their fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These results highlight the strength of our research environment and outputs, and the significant impact that our research has across the world. They demonstrate Cambridge’s leadership across a wide range of disciplines. They are testament to the imagination, visionary thinking and hard work of Cambridge researchers, who, with their many partners around the world, are making a real difference to people’s lives.” - &lt;em&gt;Vice-Chancellor Prof Stephen Toope&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cam.ac.uk/stories/REF-2021&quot;&gt;the University of Cambridge’s statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bpi-institute-narrow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The BPI building&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>/2022/05/ref-2021-results</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2022/05/ref-2021-results</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Dynamics of deep-submarine volcanic eruptions</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eric Newland, Nicola Mingotti, &lt;a href=&quot;/user/aww1&quot;&gt;Andy Woods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deposits from explosive submarine eruptions have been found in the deep sea, 1–4 km below the surface, with both flow and fall deposits extending several km’s over the seafloor. A model of a turbulent fountain suggests that after rising 10–20 m above the vent, the erupting particle-laden mixture entrains and mixes with sufficient seawater that it becomes denser than seawater. The momentum of the resulting negatively buoyant fountain is only sufficient to carry the material 50–200 m above the seafloor and much of the solid material then collapses to the seafloor; this will not produce the far-reaching fall deposits observed on the seabed. However, new laboratory experiments show that particle sedimentation at the top of the fountain enables some of the hot, buoyant water in the fountain to separate from the collapsing flow and continue rising as a buoyant plume until it forms a radially spreading intrusion higher in the water column. With eruption rates of 106–107 kg s&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;, we estimate that this warm water may rise a few 100’s m above the fountain. Some of the finer grained pyroclasts can be carried upwards by this flow and as they spread out in the radial intrusion, they gradually sediment to form a fall deposit which may extend 1000’s m from the source. Meanwhile, material collapsing from the dense fountain forms aqueous pyroclastic flows which may also spread 1000’s m from the vent forming a flow deposit on the seabed. Quantification of the controls on the concurrent fall and flow deposits, and comparison with field observations, including from the 2012 eruption of Havre Volcano in the South Pacific, open the way to new understanding of submarine eruptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-022-07351-9&quot;&gt;Article link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-masterclass-plume.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>/2022/02/deep-submarine-volcanic-eruptions</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2022/02/deep-submarine-volcanic-eruptions</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>On particle separation from turbulent particle plumes in a cross-flow</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cara James, Nicola Mingotti, &lt;a href=&quot;/user/aww1&quot;&gt;Andy Woods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Fluid Mechanics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We present new experiments of particle-driven turbulent plumes issuing from a constant source of dense particle-laden fluid, with buoyancy flux, B, in a uniform horizontal current, u. Experiments show that a turbulent, well-mixed plume develops, in which the downward vertical speed w decreases with depth z according to w = 0.76(B/uz)(1/2) while the horizontal speed rapidly asymptotes to the current speed u, provided that the Stokes settling speed of the particles v &amp;lt; 0.92w. For v &amp;gt; 0.92w, the particles separate from the plume fluid, and their depth z increases according to the simple sedimentation trajectory dz/dx = v/u. As the particles sediment, they form clusters of particles, which lead to fluctuations in the particle load with position, but do not appear to change the time-average sedimentation speed. We explore the impact of these results for deep-sea mining, in which the fate of the plume water as well as the particles is key for assessing potential environmental impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-fluid-mechanics/article/on-particle-separation-from-turbulent-particle-plumes-in-a-crossflow/0CD6E4D7D627EC92DE3514F8AAE56FED&quot;&gt;Article link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sediment-plume.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sediment plume&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>/2021/12/particle-plume-separation-paper</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/12/particle-plume-separation-paper</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>2021 Masterclass</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The Energy Masterclass is a 2 day intensive meeting of lectures and discussion, with talks from the leading experts in various aspects of energy supply and demand, with special focus on the energy transition and the technologies needed to optimise the new energy systems. There will be talks on Wind, Solar and Geothernal, Tidal and Nuclear energy, Carbon Capture and Storage, Battery Storage, Hydrogen, EV charging systems, the Transformation of the Electricity Grid, Low carbon flight, Energy Policy and the Decarbonisation of Buildings, amongst other topics, all given by leading industrialists and academics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-masterclass-plume.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>/2021/12/2021-masterclass</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/12/2021-masterclass</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Covid-19 Research</title>
				<description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;covid-19-related-research&quot;&gt;Covid 19-related research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research is ongoing on the mixing and ventilation of aerosols and viruses in buildings. Key results and publications will be added below as they become available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rspa.2020.0855&quot;&gt;The ventilation of buildings and other mitigating measures for COVID-19: a focus on wintertime&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Proc. R. Soc. A. 477), where we review knowledge of the transmission of COVID-19 indoors, examine the evidence for mitigating measures, and consider the implications for wintertime with a focus on ventilation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atsjournals.org/doi/10.1164/rccm.202009-3634LE&quot;&gt;The impact of hospital ward ventilation on airborne pathogen exposure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med., 203(6)), where we present the results of a monitoring campaign in the cystic fibrosis ward in the new Royal Papworth Hospital in Cambridge.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-fluid-mechanics/article/mixing-of-airborne-contaminants-by-the-repeated-passage-of-people-along-a-corridor/C9237DEA0C86D1EB661055D55B05E9BF&quot;&gt;The mixing of airborne contaminants by the repeated passage of people along a corridor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (J. Fluid Mech. 903), where we show that people walking through a space drive significant mixing of the air, causing viruses and aerosols to be transported long distances and remain suspended in the air for a long time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bpi.cam.ac.uk/sites/default/files/hospitalwithvoice.mp4&quot;&gt;Analogue Laboratory Modelling of Ventilation in Nightingale Hospitals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, where we compare different strategies for the ventilation of a ward.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Nzs3AwffK-Q&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;Coronavirus Pandemic: Making Safer Emergency Hospitals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Healthcare authorities are attempting to add thousands of additional bed spaces by temporarily adapting any available large open halls. Here, we compare different low-tech adaptations to ventilation systems and ward configuration.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-fluid-mechanics/article/on-the-transport-of-heavy-particles-through-an-upward-displacementventilated-space/A469E589A3DAB33799899F4581D79CD3&quot;&gt;On the transport of heavy particles through an upward displacement-ventilated space&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (J. Fluid Mech. 772), where we investigate the removal of contaminants from a warm room using displacement ventilation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-fluid-mechanics/article/on-the-transport-of-heavy-particles-through-a-downward-displacementventilated-space/766C5DC9A607B524F883496B11E6B5F2&quot;&gt;On the transport of heavy particles through a downward displacement-ventilated space&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (J. Fluid Mech. 774), where we investigate the removal of contaminants from a room containing a source of cooling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>/2021/01/covid-research</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/01/covid-research</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Comment on the BPI and Energy Transition</title>
				<description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;comment-on-the-bpi-and-energy-transition&quot;&gt;Comment on the BPI and Energy Transition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you will see from the wide range of research, we have a strong interest in helping to understand the science of climate change, including the work on ice dynamics and ocean mixing, and we have many projects related to the energy transition and the decarbonisation of the energy system, where our work is providing important new insights into new technologies, including CCS, energy storage, low energy building design, wind turbine optimisation. We also hold an annual Masterclass in Energy Supply and Demand to which all students in Cambridge can apply to attend - at this we have a host of speakers presenting the facts and data about the present and future energy system, in particular focussing on the technology and other challenges associated with decarbonising the energy system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The energy transition requires a large number of scientists and engineers to work with government, industry and society to try to assess and select optimal solutions for a decarbonised energy system. There are many choices and challenges with developing a decarbonised energy supply system and energy supply mix: it needs to have sufficient capacity to supply the energy which the world uses, both presently and going forward and we need to determine the fraction of this energy supply which each technology might contribute (eg wind or solar or geothermal or hydroelectric, or nuclear, …). Also knowledge of the present energy supply system is clearly very important in informing these decisions. On the demand side, there are very many technical challenges to develop new machines and other systems which can be powered by the new energy supply system, which will be largely delivered as electricity, or perhaps as hydrogen - compared to today, where we have a significant amount of energy delivered to the user in the form of natural gas (eg for heating over 20 million homes in the UK) or in petrol or diesel (for powering vehicles) which need to be replaced with electric vehicles or perhaps hydrogen powered vehicles, and alternative heating systems, which might include district heating systems or heat pumps, or other solutions. There are significant natural resource implications if all passenger vehicles become electric, given the large number of new batteries that we would need to manufacture. We also need new solutions for powering cargo ships and air travel. In addition, there are numerous opportunities for more efficient use of energy through new technological solutions, and better design, especially with buildings. Then the cement and steel industries, which are responsible for a significant fraction of global CO2 emissions, may require the development of CCS and the invention of lower carbon manufacturing processes. Finally, biofuels with carbon capture, offer a possible means to achieve negative emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all of these problems, there is an enormous amount of important work to be done, on policy and economics as well as the science and engineering, and we are engaged in some of these problems in the BPI. Our hope is that many students and other researchers will join in this major activity to help address both the overarching questions of technology choices moving forward (since there are many different solutions) and the detailed questions which require detailed technical / engineering or research work in each part of the energy system - both relating to the supply and the demand sides, as well as energy efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you will appreciate, industry plays a central role in the energy supply and energy demand systems, and so it is crucial that we collaborate and work constructively with industry across the whole spectrum to help translate our technical innovations into creating the new decarbonised energy system, and also to help influence the choices made by industry going forward using our detailed technical knowledge. As the energy infrastructure undergoes this enormous transition, there is a need for civilised discussion and debate, and the BPI as with other venues in the University, provides an ideal platform for such discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all want to evolve to a decarbonised energy system as rapidly as possible, but this is an enormous endeavour, and it will require tremendous innovation and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Andy Woods, April 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>/2020/04/energy-transition-comment</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/04/energy-transition-comment</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
